<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- $Id: copyright.xml,v 1.1 1998/09/01 14:47:48 lehors Exp $ -->
<!--
 *************************************************************************
 * BEGINNING OF COPYRIGHT NOTICE                                         *
 *************************************************************************
-->
<div1 id="ID-419945774">
  <head>Copyright Notice</head>

<p role='important'>Copyright &copy; 1998 <loc href="http://www.w3.org/">World Wide
Web Consortium</loc>, (<loc href="http://www.lcs.mit.edu/">Massachusetts
Institute of Technology</loc>, <loc href="http://www.inria.fr/">Institut
National de Recherche en Informatique et en Automatique</loc>, <loc
href="http://www.keio.ac.jp/">Keio University</loc>).  All Rights
Reserved.</p>

<p>Documents on the <loc href="http://www.w3.org/">W3C</loc> site are
provided by the copyright holders under the following license. By
obtaining, using and/or copying this document, or the W3C document
from which this statement is linked, you agree that you have read,
understood, and will comply with the following terms and
conditions:</p>

<p>Permission to use, copy, and distribute the contents of this
document, or the W3C document from which this statement is linked, in
any medium for any purpose and without fee or royalty is hereby
granted, provided that you include the following on <emph>ALL</emph> copies
of the document, or portions thereof, that you use:

<olist>
  <item><p>A link or URI to the original W3C document.</p></item>

  <item><p>The pre-existing copyright notice of the original author, if it
  doesn't exist, a notice of the form: &quot;Copyright &copy; <loc
  href="http://www.w3.org/">World Wide Web Consortium</loc>, (<loc
  href="http://www.lcs.mit.edu/">Massachusetts Institute of
  Technology</loc>, <loc href="http://www.inria.fr/">Institut National de
  Recherche en Informatique et en Automatique</loc>, <loc
  href="http://www.keio.ac.jp/">Keio University</loc>). All Rights
  Reserved.&quot; </p></item>

  <item><p><emph>If it exists</emph>, the STATUS of the W3C document.</p></item>
</olist></p>

<p>When space permits, inclusion of the full text of this
<emph role='important'>NOTICE</emph> should be provided. In addition, credit shall be
attributed to the copyright holders for any software, documents, or
other items or products that you create pursuant to the implementation
of the contents of this document, or any portion thereof. </p>

<p>No right to create modifications or derivatives is granted pursuant
to this license.</p>

<p role='important'>THIS DOCUMENT IS PROVIDED &quot;AS IS,&quot; AND COPYRIGHT HOLDERS
MAKE NO REPRESENTATIONS OR WARRANTIES, EXPRESS OR IMPLIED, INCLUDING,
BUT NOT LIMITED TO, WARRANTIES OF MERCHANTABILITY, FITNESS FOR A
PARTICULAR PURPOSE, NON-INFRINGEMENT, OR TITLE; THAT THE CONTENTS OF
THE DOCUMENT ARE SUITABLE FOR ANY PURPOSE; NOR THAT THE IMPLEMENTATION
OF SUCH CONTENTS WILL NOT INFRINGE ANY THIRD PARTY PATENTS,
COPYRIGHTS, TRADEMARKS OR OTHER RIGHTS.</p>

<p role='important'>COPYRIGHT HOLDERS WILL NOT BE LIABLE FOR ANY DIRECT, INDIRECT,
SPECIAL OR CONSEQUENTIAL DAMAGES ARISING OUT OF ANY USE OF THE
DOCUMENT OR THE PERFORMANCE OR IMPLEMENTATION OF THE CONTENTS
THEREOF.</p>

<p>The name and trademarks of copyright holders may NOT be used in
advertising or publicity pertaining to this document or its contents
without specific, written prior permission. Title to copyright in this
document will at all times remain with copyright holders. </p>
</div1>
<!--
 *************************************************************************
 * END OF COPYRIGHT NOTICE                                               *
 *************************************************************************
-->
