<!-- $Date: 1998/09/23 14:14:55 $ $Revision: 1.12 $ -->
<div1 id="ID-2010795334" role="note">
  <head>Production Notes (Non-Normative)</head>
  <orglist role="editors">
    <member>
      <name>Gavin Nicol</name>
      <affiliation>Inso EPS</affiliation>
    </member>
  </orglist>
  <p>The DOM specification serves as a good example of the power of
    using XML: all of the HTML documents, Java bindings, OMG IDL bindings, and
    ECMA Script bindings are generated from a single set of XML source
    files. This section outlines how this specification is written in
    XML, and how the various derived works are created. </p>
  <div2 id="ID-1181349559">
    <head>The Document Type Definition</head> 
    <p>This specification was written entirely in XML, using a DTD based
      heavily on the DTD used by the XML Working Group for the XML
      specification. The major difference between the DTD used by the XML
      Working Group, and the DTD used for this specification is the
      addition of a DTD module for interface specifications.</p>
    <p>The DTD module for interfaces specifications is a very loose
      translation of the Extended Backus-Naur Form (EBNF)
      specification of the OMG IDL syntax into XML DTD syntax. In
      addition to the translation, the ability to
      <emph>describe</emph> the interfaces was added, thereby creating
      a limited form of <emph>literate programming</emph> for
      interface definitions.</p>
    <p>While the DTD module is sufficient for the purposes of the DOM
      WG, it is very loosely typed, meaning that there are very few
      constraints placed on the type specifications (the type
      information is effectively treated as an opaque string). In a DTD 
      for object
      to object communication, some stricter enforcement of data types
      would probably be beneficial.</p>
  </div2>
  <div2 id="ID-934280754">
    <head>The production process</head>
    <p>The DOM specification is written using XML. All documents are valid
      XML. In order to produce
      the HTML versions of the specification, the object indexes, the Java
      source code, and the OMG IDL and ECMA Script
      definitions, the XML specification is <emph>converted</emph>.</p>
    <p>The tool currently used for conversion is <emph>COST</emph> by
      Joe English. <code>COST</code> takes the ESIS output of
      <code>nsgmls</code>, creates an internal representation, and
      then allows <emph>scripts</emph>, and <emph>event
	handlers</emph> to be run over the internal data structure.
      Event handlers allow document <emph>patterns</emph> and
      associated processing to be specified: when the pattern is
      matched during a pre-order traversal of a document subtree, the
      associated action is executed. This is the heart of the
      conversion process. Scripts are used to tie the various
      components together. For example, each of the major derived data
      sources (Java code etc.) is created by the execution of a
      script, which in turn executes one or more event handlers. The
      scripts and event handlers are specified using TCL.</p>
    <p>The current version of <code>COST</code> has been somewhat
      modified from the publicly available version. In particular,
      it now runs correctly under 32-bit Windows, uses TCL 8.0, and 
      correctly handles the case sensitivity of
      XML (though it probably could not correctly handle native language
      markup).</p>
    <p>We could also have used <code>Jade</code>, by James Clark. Like
      <code>COST</code>, <code>Jade</code> allows patterns and actions
      to be specified, but <code>Jade</code> is based on DSSSL, an
      international standard, whereas <code>COST</code> is
      not. <code>Jade</code> is more powerful than <code>COST</code>
      in many ways, but prior experience of the editor with Cost made it 
      easier to use this rather than <code>Jade</code>. A future version 
      or Level of
      the DOM specification may be produced using <code>Jade</code> or
      an <code>XSL</code> processor.</p>
    <p>The complete XML source files are available at: <loc
	href="xml-source.zip">&w3c.url;/xml-source.zip</loc></p>
  </div2>
  <div2 id="ID-235933356">
    <head>Object Definitions</head>
    <p>As stated earlier, all object definitions are specified in XML.
      The Java bindings, OMG IDL bindings, and ECMA Script bindings are all
      generated automatically from the XML source code.</p>
    <p>This is possible because the information specified in XML is a
      <emph>superset</emph> of what these other syntax need. This is a
      general observation, and the same kind of technique can be
      applied to many other areas: given rich structure, rich
      processing and conversion are possible. For Java and OMG IDL, it
      is basically just a matter of renaming syntactic keywords; for
      ECMA Script, the process is somewhat more involved.</p>
    <p>A typical object definition in XML looks something like this:
<eg role="code">
&lt;interface name="foo">
  &lt;descr>&lt;p>Description goes here...&lt;/p>&lt;/descr>
  &lt;method name="bar">
    &lt;descr>&lt;p>Description goes here...&lt;/p>&lt;/descr>
    &lt;parameters>
      &lt;param name="baz" type="DOMString" attr="in">
        &lt;descr>&lt;p>Description goes here...&lt;/p>&lt;/descr>
      &lt;/param>
    &lt;/parameters>
    &lt;returns type="void">
       &lt;descr>&lt;p>Description goes here...&lt;/p>&lt;/descr>
    &lt;/returns>
    &lt;raises>
       &lt;!-- Throws no exceptions -->  
    &lt;/raises>
  &lt;/method>
&lt;/interface></eg></p>
    <p>As can easily be seen, this is quite verbose, but not unlike
      OMG IDL. In fact, when the specification was originally
      converted to use XML, the OMG IDL definitions were automatically
      converted into the corresponding XML source using common Unix text
      manipulation tools.</p>
    </div2>
</div1>
 
